A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of the Secretary, Grants Processing Unit Files FA1522
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of the Secretary, Grants Processing Unit Files
1961-1989
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA1522
12.4 Cubic Feet 33 boxes (32 letter document containers and 1 half-letter document container)
Biographical / Historical
The Ford Foundation was chartered by Henry and Edsel Ford in 1936 "to receive and administer funds for scientific, educational and charitable purposes, all for the public welfare", and initially served the Ford family's charitable interests in the Detroit area. Following the deaths of Edsel Ford (1943) and Henry Ford (1947), the Foundation was propelled to the forefront of philanthropy as the largest American foundation in terms of both endowment and yearly expenditures, and with an international scope to its major program areas. During the Foundation's first twenty years its major programs were in international economic development, primary and higher education, educational and public broadcasting, behavioral sciences, civil liberties, urban development, fine arts and the humanities. The Ford Foundation also partnered with the Rockefeller Foundation in supporting agricultural development in South America, Africa, and Southeast Asia. Since the 1970s, the Foundation has also pioneered programs in women's rights, energy policy, micro-financing in under-developed countries, establishing human rights groups, and improving international HIV/AIDS education.
Scope and Contents
The Office of the Secretary was established in 1950 and the Office of the General Counsel was established in 1971. The two offices merged in the early 1980s. The Grants Processing Unit within the Office of the Secretary was responsible for maintaining official copies of Recommended Grant Actions forms and Delegated Authority Projects, memoranda, and official files relating to the tax status and classification of grantee organizations.
The collection reflects the activities of the Office of the Secretary. The collection contains grant forms used by the Ford Foundation, grant notification letters, grant application materials, meeting materials, correspondence, and memos.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into four series:
Series 1: General Grant Files
Series 2: Grants Out of Appropriations
Series 3: Officer Grants
Series 4: Overseas Development Grants
The collection is arranged chronologically. The physical arrangement of the collection does not match its intellectual arrangement because the collection is comprised of several accessions that did not come to the RAC in a consistent, chronological order.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This material was transferred to RAC in 2019 by the Ford Foundation and ingested by RAC as Accessions 2019:029, 2019:049, and 2019:069.
Ford Foundation; Grants
- General Grant Files, 1987; 1
  - Program Action Forms, Grant Notification Letters, and Delegated Authority Grant (DAG) Memos - Com-Z, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 1-4, Box 2, Folder 4-6, Box 3, Folder 7-10, Box 4, Folder 11-14, Box 5, Folder 15-18, Box 6, Folder 19-23, Box 7, Folder 24-26, Box 8, Folder 27-31, Box 9, Folder 32)
    Arrangement
    Folders are arranged alphabetically
- Grants Out of Appropriations, 1963-1989; 2
  - Program Actions Out of Appropriation - Fiscal Year 1964, 1963 October 1-1964 June 31 (Box 21, Folder 79-81)
  - Grants and Projects Out of Appropriation - Fiscal Year 1964, 1964 July 1-September 30 (Box 29, Folder 108)
  - Program Actions Out of Appropriation - Fiscal Year 1965, 1964 October 1-1965 September 30 (Box 21, Folder 82, Box 22, Folder 83-84)
  - Grants and Projects Out of Appropriation - Fiscal Year 1975 (Books 1-3), 1974 October-November (Box 22, Folder 85-86, Box 23, Folder 87-89)
  - Grants and Projects Out of Appropriation - Fiscal Year 1975 (Book 4), 1974 December 6-19 (Box 23, Folder 90, Box 24, Folder 91)
  - Grants and Projects Out of Appropriation - Fiscal Year 1975 (Book 5), 1975 January 2-30 (Box 24, Folder 92)
  - Grants and Projects Out of Appropriation - Fiscal Year 1975 (Book 6), 1975 February 6-27 (Box 24, Folder 93, Box 25, Folder 94)
  - Grants and Projects Out of Appropriation - Fiscal Year 1975 (Book 7), 1975 March 6-20 (Box 25, Folder 95)
  - Grants and Projects Out of Appropriation - Fiscal Year 1975 (Book 8), 1975 April 3-24 (Box 25, Folder 96)
  - Grants Out of Appropriation - A-Z, 1976 (Box 26, Folder 97-99, Box 27, Folder 100-102, Box 28, Folder 103-105)
  - Delegated Authority Projects, 1976 (Box 29, Folder 106)
  - Grants Out of Appropriations, 1986 March-December (Box 10, Folder 33-35, Box 11, Folder 36-40, Box 12, Folder 41-44, Box 13, Folder 45-49)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes official copies of Recommendation for Grant Action forms (RGAs)
    Folder title refers to the date the RGAs were discussed at Ford Foundation officers' meetings. Meeting agendas can be found at the front of each folder with a listing of the RGAs relevant to each particular meeting.
    Materials are arranged chronologically by date grants were discussed at Ford Foundation officers' meetings.
  - Grants Out of Appropriations, 1987 January-September (Box 14, Folder 50-54, Box 15, Folder 55-58, Box 16, Folder 59-61, Box 17, Folder 62-65, Box 18, Folder 66)
    The folder title refers to the date the RGAs were discussed at Ford Foundation officers' meetings. Meeting agendas can be found at the front of each folder with a listing of the RGAs relevant to each particular meeting.
  - Grants Out of Appropriations, 1988 October-December (Box 18, Folder 67-70, Box 19, Folder 71-72)
  - Grants Out of Appropriations, 1989 January-March (Box 19, Folder 73-74, Box 20, Folder 75-78)
- Officer Grants, 1961-1965; 3
  - Officers' Meetings - Fiscal Year 1961 and 1962, 1961-1962 (Box 29, Folder 107)
  - Officer Grants, 1963 October 1-1964 March 31 (Box 29, Folder 109)
  - Officer Grants, 1964 April 1-September 30 (Box 29, Folder 110)
  - Officer Grants, 1964 October 1-1965 March 31 (Box 29, Folder 111)
  - Officer Grants - Fiscal Year 1965, 1965 April 1-September 30 (Box 29, Folder 112)
- Overseas Development Grants, 1963-1965; 4
  - Overseas Development Grant Records, 1963 April-December (Box 30, Folder 113-117)
  - Overseas Development Grant Records, 1964 January-September (Box 31, Folder 118-120, Box 32, Folder 121-122)
  - Overseas Development Grant Records, 1964 December-1965 March (Box 33, Folder 125)
  - Overseas Development Grant Records, 1965 April-September (Box 32, Folder 123-124)
  - Financial Regulations - Ford Foundation Public Administration Project - Riyadh, Saudi Arabia, undated (Box 33, Folder 126)